Feinstein International Center Records UA197
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
- White papers, UA197.000267
  - Impact Assessment, 2005 -- 2011; UA197.014; 4 Digital Object(s)
    - Impact Assessments of Livelihoods-based Drought Interventions in Moyale and Dire Woredas, 2007-03-15; UA197.014.014.00005; Catley, Andrew
      The Pastoralist Livelihoods Initiative (PLI) is a two-year program funded by USAID Ethiopia which combines field level implementation and learning in pastoral areas, with the development of national guidelines for livelihoods-based Livestock relief interventions with the Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Development. From late 2005 into 2006 a severe drought affected some pastoral areas of southern Ethiopia, and PLI government and NGO partners intervened with various types of Livestock-related assistance. With the intention of informing policy dialogue and contributing to the national guidelines, Impact assessments were then conducted in two woredas. The Impact assessments combined descriptions of project activities (sometimes called 'process monitoring') with the systematic use of participatory methods to capture local perceptions of benefits.
    - Impact Assessment of the Community Animal Health System in Mandera West District, Kenya, 2009-10-02; UA197.014.014.00006; Bekele, Gezu; Akumu, Jeremiah
      The pastoralist communities in Kenya's arid lands rely on their Livestock for food and income, and basic veterinary care is one of the best ways to protect Livestock assets and pastoralist livelihoods in these areas. This report examines the impact of a privatized, community-based veterinary service in the far northeast of Kenya, and focuses on the outcomes of clinical services provided by community-based Animal health workers (CAHWs). Fatality rates in herds in treated by CAHWs using medicines from rural pharmacies were significantly lower than in herds where treatments were provided by untrained Livestock keepers. The report adds to the substantial body of evidence already collected in Kenya on the impact and financial rationale for CAHW systems. Although many other countries have now legalized these systems and developed national guidelines for CAHW training, Kenya has yet to officially recognize CAHWs and overall, veterinary services in pastoralist areas often remain in the hands of untrained workers and unlicensed drug vendors.
    - Addressing Integrated Coordination in Food Security Crises, 2011-11-28; UA197.014.014.00007; Maxwell, Daniel; Parker, John
      In May 2011, the Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO) and World Food Programme (WFP) formally launched the global Food Security Cluster (FSC) as the UNs global mechanism for coordinating food security responses in emergencies. The creation of the global cluster coincides with a period in which the number of food security actors has continued to grow, the operating environment has become more complex, and the range of responses has required greater levels of skill in analysis, planning, implementation and monitoring. All of this underscores the need for greater coordination. This paper summarizes the mandate of the newly formed global FSC, presents an analysis of the major issues and challenges it faces, and provides recommendations to donors and the global FSC for possible ways to address these issues. Issues addressed include the leadership of clusters and coordination; coordination linkages and challenges at the global level; transitions, exit and the boundaries of food security coordination in emergencies; accountability, effectiveness and funding. Addressing many of these issues will require broader coordination among actors and institutions that do not necessarily have similarly-aligned interests and incentives. However, the global FSC itself can do several things. First, given the myriad issues the global FSC faces, the cluster leadership can provide some strategic prioritizing. Second, while clusters exist for humanitarian purposes, it is clear that cluster coordination is more effective when good preparedness plans are in place and where longer-term concerns are taken into consideration in the acute emergency response. Finally, good leadership in the right place at the right time is a key component of an effective response and effective coordination, and ensuring this leadership is one of the challenges facing the global Cluster. Donors can provide support to the global FSC making clear the priorities they see at the global level and engaging at the country level where capacity exists; by supporting the global FSC to function as a main repository of experience and lessons learned; and by ensuring the expertise for innovative approaches is critical for strategic success.
  - Targeting in Complex Emergencies, 2008 -- 2009; UA197.015; 4 Digital Object(s)
    This series contains reports related to the Targeting in Complex Emergencies project.
    - Targeting in Complex Emergencies: Somalia Country Case Study, 2008-08-05; UA197.015.015.00001; Jaspars, Susanne; Maxwell, Daniel
      This study examined community participation throughout the Food relief program cycle to understand the role of recipient communities in the targeting of food assistance under the Conflict, Armed (War) conditions in Somalia, a country that has not had a central government since the fall of the President Siad Barre in 1991. Security considerations, limited staff numbers and other constraints have long meant that the actual oversight of what happens with Food relief must be left in the hands of local leaders at the village or camp level. The study found big differences in the accountability and legitimacy of local leadership in different locations, from clan elders and religious leaders in some locations, to "gate keepers" who control information, access, and resources in other locations, especially in IDP camps. Though "committees" of "local leaders" exist in both situations, the degree to which leaders actually represent the "community" differs enormously. The practice of redistribution of food assistance limits the number of people in any recipient community who are excluded from food assistance, but also ends up ensuring that no one receives very much. Most communities hold strong views that external assistance in the form of food should be shared equally within communities. But much of the process of Food relief targeting remains opaque to recipients. They are often not aware of their entitlements or the process of determining who is entitled. The report makes various suggestions for improving participation in targeting, and improving targeting generally.
    - Targeting in Complex Emergencies: Darfur Case Study, 2009-05-12; UA197.015.015.00002; Young, Helen; Maxwell, Daniel
      This study examined community participation throughout the Food relief program cycle to understand the role of recipient communities in the targeting of food assistance under the Conflict, Armed (War) conditions in Darfur - one of the largest Food relief programs in the world. The Darfur Conflict, Armed (War) is now in its sixth year, and has drawn in a complex web of local, national, and transnational interests, which play out in different types of inter-connected Conflict, Armed (War) throughout the region. From the start of the Conflict, Armed (War) in 2003, protection threats and restricted access have been major challenges to the humanitarian community.
    - Targeting in Complex Emergencies: South Sudan Country Case Study, 2008-07-28; UA197.015.015.00003; Maxwell, Daniel; Burns, John
      The population of Southern Sudan was caught in a civil war from 1983 to 2005. During the war, several major famines led to a massive Food relief intervention by the World Food Programme – intervention that continues to the present. Much of this food was delivered to vulnerable people by air drops, with the actual targeting of assistance on the ground left to local leaders and traditional authorities. The main objective of targeting was to minimize exclusion.
    - Targeting in Complex Emergencies: Colombia Country Case Study, 2009-05-26; UA197.015.015.00004; Frize, Jacqueline
      Can community-based approaches to the targeting of humanitarian assistance in complex emergencies improve participation and reduce targeting error? Although the literature suggests that community-based targeting works best in slow-onset emergencies with no Conflict, Armed (War) or Forced Human beings--Migrations, participatory approaches to targeting assistance have been attempted in complex emergencies. This study examined the participation of displaced communities through the Food relief program cycle with particular attention to its different steps (early warning, needs assessment, design, targeting criteria, beneficiary identification and selection, distribution, monitoring and evaluation).
  - Humanitarian Horizons, 2009 -- 2010; UA197.016; 5 Digital Object(s)
    This series contains reports related to the Humanitarian Horizons project.
    - Climate Change and its Humanitarian Impacts, 2009-11-05; UA197.016.016.00001; Morinière, Lezlie C. Erway; Taylor, Richard; Hamza, Mohamed; Downing, Tom
      Global climate change will have inevitable consequences and implications for the humanitarian community. Although specific outcomes are unclear, it is certain that the world will experience significant transformations in the next 20 years, and that currently vulnerable populations will be among those most affected. Researchers from the Stockholm Environment Institute, as the authors of this paper, describe the current state of climate information, and the expected human and physical consequences for which humanitarian organizations must be prepared to address in the next two decades.
    - Demographic Trends and their Humanitarian Impacts, 2009-11-12; UA197.016.016.00002; Haub, Carl
      Expected demographic trends of the future include unprecedented population growth, the majority of which will occur in developing countries, and which will lead to a "demographic crisis" in Sub-Saharan Africa. The humanitarian implications of this growth, and its regional disparities, will be manifold, as described by researcher Carl Haub, of the Population Reference Bureau.
      Demography; Humanitarian Assistance; Feinstein International Center
    - The Future of Globalization and its Humanitarian Impacts, 2009-11-05; UA197.016.016.00003; Khan, Shanza; Najam, Adil
      More than simply an economic phenomenon, globalization is a multi-faceted and dynamic process with implications for future Human beings--Migrations and mobility, technological expansion, and worldwide social inequality. With an eye on the many possible futures of globalization, the authors of this paper consider the likely consequences of each for the humanitarian community.
      Globalization; Feinstein International Center
    - Future of the Humanitarian System: Impacts of Internal Changes, 2009-11-12; UA197.016.016.00004; Borton, John
      t only affected by the trends and events that occur within the world in which it operates, the humanitarian system is equally affected by those developments and trends that take place inside the organizations and networks comprising the system. In this paper, John Borton describes these internal dynamics - including the conflation of "humanitarian" and "development", shrinking humanitarian space, and issues of accountability - and creates a picture of future humanitarian response in light of these changes.
    - Humanitarian Horizons: A Practitioners' Guide to the Future, 2010-01-25; UA197.016.016.00005; Feinstein International Center; Humanitarian Futures Programme
      This Practitioners' Guide to the Future serves as the culmination of the Humanitarian Horizons project, commissioned by the members of the Inter-Agency Working Group and implemented jointly by the Feinstein International Center (FIC) and the Humanitarian Futures Programme (HFP) of King's College, London. The Guide merges the projections of global change highlighted by four earlier research papers, with the futures perspectives of operational agencies. The result is an attempt to help Humanitarian assistance agencies look a generation into the future to begin making the necessary changes now to their thinking and organization, to ensure that they continue to deliver the right assistance and protection to the right people in the right ways.
  - Aid and Security, 2010 -- 2011; UA197.017; 4 Digital Object(s)
    This series contains reports related to the Aid & Security project.
    - Winning Hearts and Minds? Examining the Relationship Between Aid and Security in Kenya, 2010-04-08; UA197.017.017.00001; Bradbury, Mark; Kleinman, Michael
      Since the late 1990's Kenya's large and thinly populated northeastern region bordering Somalia has become a focus for US government efforts in Africa to counter terrorism, mitigate violent extremism and promote stability and governance. This paper examines the effectiveness of one aspect of those efforts, namely the aid projects implemented by US Civil Affairs teams deployed from the Combined Joint Task Force-Horn of Africa (CJTF-HOA) in Garissa and Wajir districts in North Eastern province, and Lamu district in Coast province. The paper argues that these activities were useful at a tactical level in terms of facilitating the US military's entry into regions of potential concern, and in helping them to acquire local knowledge and connections. However, it also highlights some of the limitations at a strategic level of using foreign aid as a tool for countering terrorism or insurgencies and promoting stability and security. For example, the research found that these small-scale and scattered projects did little to win hearts and minds or change perceptions of the US in the communities where the projects were implemented. There was also little evidence that the projects had contributed to improved security by addressing some of the perceived underlying causes of terrorism and violent extremism in the region.
      Conflict, Armed (War); Human Security; Feinstein International Center
    - Winning Hearts and Minds in Afghanistan? Examining the Relationship between Aid and Security in Balkh Province, 2010-11-08; UA197.017.017.00002; Fishstein, Paul
      Afghanistan has been a testing ground for a key aspect of counterinsurgency doctrine, namely that humanitarian and development projects can help to bring or maintain security in strategically important environments, and by "winning hearts and minds" undermine support for radical, insurgent, or terrorist groups. The assumption that aid projects improve security has lead to a sharp increase in overall development funding, an increased percentage of activities programmed based on strategic security considerations, and a shift of development activities to the military. Given what is at stake, it is essential that policy makers understand whether and how aid projects can actually contribute to security.
    - Winning Hearts and Minds? Examining the Relationship between Aid and Security in Afghanistan's Faryab Province, 2011-01-19; UA197.017.017.00003; Gompleman, Geert
      Afghanistan has been a testing ground for a key aspect of counterinsurgency doctrine, namely that humanitarian and development projects can help to bring or maintain security in strategically important environments, and by "winning hearts and minds" undermine support for radical, insurgent, or terrorist groups. The assumption that aid projects improve security has lead to a sharp increase in overall development funding, an increased percentage of activities programmed based on strategic security considerations, and a shift of development activities to the military. Given what is at stake, it is essential that policy makers understand whether and how aid projects can actually contribute to security. This second provincial case study examines the drivers of insecurity, characteristics of aid projects and aid implementers, and effects of aid projects on the popularity of aid actors and on security in an area of Afghanistan which has been among the most peaceful, but which has significant pockets of insecurity. Faryab differs from the other provinces in that the Norwegian-led Provincial Reconstruction Team (PRT) does not have a civil-military coordination function and does not directly implement development projects, instead channeling its aid through the central government, multi-lateral institutions, and non-governmental organizations.
    - Winning Hearts and Minds? Examining the Relationship between Aid and Security in Afghanistans Helmand Province, 2011-05-03; UA197.017.017.00004; Gordon, Stuart
      Afghanistan has been a testing ground for a key aspect of counterinsurgency doctrine, namely that humanitarian and development projects can help to bring or maintain security in strategically important environments, and by winning hearts and minds undermine support for radical, insurgent, or terrorist groups. The assumption that aid projects improve security has lead to a sharp increase in overall development funding, an increased percentage of activities programmed based on strategic security considerations, and a shift of development activities to the military. Given what is at stake, it is essential that policy makers understand whether and how aid projects can actually contribute to security. This third Afghanistan provincial case study examines the use of aid, including "Quick Impact Projects" (QIPS), from 2006-08 to attempt to produce stability in an area of Afghanistan which has been among the most insecure and which has been a major focus of financial and human resources.
  - Milk Matters, 2009 -- 2011; UA197.018; 3 Digital Object(s)
    This series contains reports related to the Milk Matters project.
    - Milk Matters: The Role and Value of Milk in the Diets of Somali Pastoralist Children in Liben and Shinile, Ethiopia, 2009-11-02; UA197.018.018.00001; Sadler, Kate; Catley, Andrew
      This report is the outcome of the first phase of Milk Matters: a joint venture between the Feinstein International Center, Save the Children USA and Save the Children UK in Ethiopia. Milk Matters ultimately aims to improve the Nutritional status of Children--Crimes against in pastoralist/semi pastoralist areas in the horn of Africa. Based on work conducted in Shinile and Liben Zones of Somali Region Ethiopia, this study aimed to ask pastoralist women and men what they think about important causes of child malNutrition, links between child Nutritional status and animal milk supply, and "best bet" interventions for addressing malNutrition in their communities.
      Children--Nutrition; Feinstein International Center
    - Milk Matters: A Literature Review of Pastoralist Nutrition and Programming Responses, 2009-05-06; UA197.018.018.00002; Sadler, Kate; Kerven, Carol; Calo, Muriel; Manske, Michael; Catley, Andrew
      Children across pastoralist/semi pastoralist areas of the horn of Africa are often referred to as some of the most Nutritionally vulnerable in the world. The dominant response from the international community to malNutrition in these areas continues to be the delivery of large quantities of Food relief each time rains fail and rates of acute malNutrition peak. Despite acceptance of the urgent need for risk reduction and drought mitigation there is still little understanding of the causes of malNutrition, and which interventions in the medium to long term should be prioritized to improve the health and Nutritional status of Children--Crimes against in these settings.
    - Milk Matters in Karamoja: Milk in Childrens Diets and Household Livelihoods, 2011-10-17; UA197.018.018.00003; Stites, Elizabeth; Mitchard, Emily
      This study, the latest under the collaborative initiative between the Feinstein International Center and Save the Children, examines changes in milk supply and uses by households in pastoral, agro-pastoral and agricultural livelihood zones in Karamoja. Using participatory methods of data collection, the research illustrates both how significant the loss of milk has been to diets and livelihoods and how households have responded to this loss. We find that households prioritize feeding any available milk to children at the expense of milk for all other household members and all other purposes. Nevertheless, the overall reduction of milk in the diets of children continues to have serious nutritional consequences that warrant further attention at the programming, policy and advocacy levels.
  - Humanitarian Action and Response, 2000 -- 2004; UA197.019; 4 Digital Object(s)
    This series contains reports related to the Humanitarian Action and Response project.
    - Mapping the future capacities of the International Federation of Red Cross and Red Crescent Societies, 2004-03-26; UA197.019.019.00001; Feinstein International Center
      The Norwegian Red Cross, a member of the IFRC, has contacted the Feinstein Famine Center, asking it to lead a dedicated research process to propose areas where National Societies' special skills and strengths might be further utilised within the framework of the Federation, to suggest new modes of cooperation within the Federation, to analyze the cost benefits of providing certain key Federal services through individual members or small consortia, and finally to look at new modalities for financing, staffing and managing Federation national and regional delegations.
      Humanitarian Assistance; Red Cross and Red Crescent; Feinstein International Center
    - The Famine in North Korea: Humanitarian Responses in Communist Nations, 2000-02-07; UA197.019.019.00002; Lautze, Sue
      This issues paper is intended to raise awareness and encourage debate about the current crisis in the Democratic People's Republic of Korea (DPRK). Given the level of controversy about humanitarian interventions in North Korea, Lautze, Sue has attempted to provide a framework for analyzing the complicated and unique political, military and economic factors not common to emergencies elsewhere in the world. What is presented here should not be interpreted as fully confirmed, solid fact. Indeed, no information about North Korea should be taken as such. Instead, she has sought to provide an alternative, if controversial, methodology of interpreting and monitoring famine in North Korea. This multi-dimensional approach to understanding the intricacies of today's crises is in line with the Center's overall strategy to promote more effective responses to disasters.
      Famine; Food security; Humanitarian Assistance; Feinstein International Center
    - The Future of Humanitarian Action: Implications of Iraq and Other Recent Crises, 2004-01-14; UA197.019.019.00003; Feinstein International Center
      This report summarizes a round of consultations organized by the Feinstein International Famine Center (FIFC) in cooperation with other institutions the InterAgency Standing Committee, The Overseas Development Institute, Oxfam, and the Brookings Institution, on the implications of Iraq and other recent crises for the future of humanitarian action. It builds on an Issues Note prepared by FIFC for a workshop convened by the FIFC on October 9, 2003 in Boston and incorporates material from subsequent meetings and consultations as well as comments received from a wide range of humanitarian practitioners. The dates and locations of the consultations are described in Annex II.
    - The International Operational Response to the Psychological Wounds of War: Understanding and Improving the Psycho-social Interventions, 2002-01-25; UA197.019.019.00004; McDonald, Laura